Guide to the Joseph Nechvatal Papers MSS.338
Fales Library and Special Collections
Joseph Nechvatal Papers
1970-2022
Fales Library and Special Collections
Nechvatal, Joseph
MSS.338
11.25 Linear Feet in 18 manuscript boxes, 2 card boxes, 2 half manuscript boxes, 1 flat box, 1 record carton, 2 flat file folders, and 12 folders in shared boxes.
20 audiocassettes
20 electronic discs (cd-rom)
18 3.5" floppy disks
12 film reels
6 videocassettes (vhs)
5 videodiscs (dvd)
4 videocassettes (u-matic)
4 sound discs (cd)
2 videocassettes (betamax)
1 sound cassettes (dat)
1 videocassettes (minidv)
1 sound tape reels
860 Megabytes in 6 zip disks.
88 Megabytes in 1 removable cartridge.
837.8 Megabytes in 165 computer files
The collection consists of personal and professional materials Joseph Nechvatal created and gathered throughout his career as an artist and professor. The collection primarily consists of publications, ephemera, and photographic materials pertaining to Nechvatal's research and artistic work. The collection also contains a large portion of audio recordings, video recordings, and born-digital materials related to Nechvatal's art. To a lesser extent, collection materials include correspondence, artwork, sketchbooks, and financial documents. The materials date from 1970 to 2012.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Joseph Nechvatal, 2012. The accession number associated with this gift is 2012.338. In November 2022 Nechvatal donated an accretion; the accession number associated with this gift is 2023.010.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
Joseph Nechvatal is a post-conceptual digital artist and art theoretician who creates computer-assisted paintings and computer animations, often using custom-created computer viruses. Nechavatal studied fine art at Southern Illinois University and earned his Ph.D. in the philosophy of art and new technology at The Centre for Advanced Inquiry in the Interactive Arts at the University of Wales, Newport, UK.
Since 1986 Nechvatal has worked with ubiquitous electronic visual information, computers and computer-robotics. His computer-robotic assisted paintings and computer software animations are shown regularly in galleries and museums throughout the world. From 1991-1993 he worked as artist-in-resident at the Louis Pasteur Atelier in Arbois, France and at the Saline Royale/Ledoux Foundation's computer lab. There he worked on The Computer Virus Project, which was an artistic experiment with computer viruses and computer animation. In 2002, he extended that artistic research into the field of viral artificial life through his collaboration with the programmer Stéphane Sikora.
From 1999 to 2013 Nechvatal taught at the School of Visual Arts in New York City. He has also published several works including his book of essays Towards an Immersive Intelligence: Essays on the Work of Art in the Age of Computer Technology and Virtual Reality (1993-2006), Immersion Into Noise, Minóy, and Destroyer of Naivetés.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact fales.library@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact fales.library@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of personal and professional materials Nechvatal created and gathered throughout his career as an artist and professor. Nechvatal's papers contain a large amount of publications, ephemera, and clippings that Nechvatal wrote himself or was featured in. The collection also contains a large amount of photographic materials, audiovisual materials, and born-digital materials related to his artistic works. To a lesser extent, the collection consists of Nechvatal's personal correspondence, original drawings, receipts, invoices, and his sketchbooks with notes and sketches for his various artistic projects.
Collection materials include exhibition catalogs, journals, books, clippings, flyers, invitations, programs, posters, photographs, transparencies, negatives, slides, correspondence, sketchbooks, receipts, invoices, and artwork. Audiovisual and born-digital materials in the collection include audiocassette tapes, videocassette tapes, film reels, open reel audio, compact discs, DVDs, floppy disks, and zip disks. Materials in the collection date from 1970 to 2012. Some materials are in French.
Artists -- United States.; Computer artists.; Art, American -- 20th century; Art, American -- 21st century; Computer art.; Nechvatal, Joseph
- Publications, 1988-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
- Receipts and invoices, 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Ephemera, correspondence, and clippings, 1984-2012 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
- Invitations, degrees, and researcher card, 1999-2009 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Ephemera, correspondence, and press releases, 1982-2012 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
- Ephemera, correspondence, clippings, and receipts, 1993-2011 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Publications and clippings, 1977-2007 (Box 2, Folder 2-4)
- Ephemera, receipts, and contracts, 2004-2009 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Publications, articles, and notes, 1990-2000 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Ephemera, clippings, and correspondence, 2000-2010 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
- Publications and ephemera, 1993-2005 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Portrait of Marie Claude Benichou Nechvatal, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Publications, 1995-2005 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- XS the Opera, 1984-1991 (Box 3, Folder 2-4)
- Photographs and negatives, undated (Box 3, Folder 5-8)
- Morocco negatives, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Computer virus project, 1988-2012 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Publications and ephemera, 1984-2012 (Box 3, Folder 11-13)
- Photographs, transparencies, and negatives, 1982-1985 (Box 4, Folder 1-5)
- Ephemera, publications, and clippings, 1983-1991 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
- Slides, transparencies, and photographs, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Ephemera and publications, 1985-1991 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Metabody, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Photographs, transparencies, and negatives, 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
- Drawings, 1982-1989 (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
- Publications, ephemera, and photographs, 1983-1991 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
- Ephemera, clippings, and transparencies, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Southern Illinois University diploma, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Publications, 1984-1993 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
- Towards an Immersive Intelligence typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Ephemera, clippings, and correspondence, 2000-2009 (Box 5, Folder 10-12)
- Ephemera, clippings, correspondence, and publications, 1985-2008 (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
- Genetic code certificate, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Ephemera, clippings, correspondence, and publications, 1982-2012 (Box 6, Folder 6-10)
- Ephemera and publications, 1979-1998 (Box 7, Folder 1-9)
- Ephemera and publications, 1985-2001 (Box 8, Folder 1-7)
- Slides, 1974-1994 (Box 9, Folder 1-21)
- Photographs, negatives, and slides, 1970-1995 (Box 10, Folder 1-18)
- Photographs, negatives, and transparencies, 1984-1992 (Box 11, Folder 1-18)
- Photographs, negatives, transparencies, and slides, 1983-1992 (Box 12, Folder 1-31)
- Photographs, negatives, transparencies, and slides, 1979-1994 (Box 13, Folder 1-22)
- Ephemera, photographs, and transparencies, 1984-2009 (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
- Correspondence, 1987-1997 (Box 14, Folder 4-6)
- Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 15, Folder 1-9)
- Publications, 1985 (Box Shared Fales 017, Folder 2)
- Transparencies, undated (Box Shared Fales 017, Folder 3-5)
- Photographs, 1986 (Box Shared Fales 001, Folder 12-16)
- Posters, 1990-2004 (Box Shared Fales 001, Folder 11)
- Posters, 1977-2010 (Box Shared Fales 004, Folder 8)
- Posters, 1986-2004 (Flat-file-folder 3)
- Drawing, undated (Flat-file-folder 21)
- Drawing, 1981 (Box Shared Fales 004, Folder 9)
- Audiovisual materials, 1979-2006; 20 audiocassettes; 12 film reels; 6 videocassettes (vhs); 5 videodiscs (dvd); 4 videocassettes (u-matic); 4 sound discs (cd); 2 videocassettes (betamax); 1 sound cassettes (dat); 1 videocassettes (minidv); 1 sound tape reels (Box 16, Box 17, Box 18)
- Born-digital materials, 1979-2006; 20 electronic discs (cd-rom); 18 3.5" floppy disks; 860 Megabytes in 6 zip disks.; 88 Megabytes in 1 removable cartridge. (Box 17, Box 18)
- Ceramic mask, undated (Box 19)
- Metal figurine, undated (Box 19)
- Sketchbook, 1974 (Box 20, Folder 1)
- Sketchbook, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 2)
- Sketchbook, 1976 (Box 20, Folder 3)
- Sketchbook, 1977 (Box 20, Folder 4)
- Sketchbook, 1978 (Box 21, Folder 1)
- Sketchbook, 1978 (Box 21, Folder 2)
- Sketchbook, 1979 (Box 21, Folder 3)
- Sketchbook, 1980 (Box 21, Folder 4)
- Sketchbook, 1999, 2003-2006 (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
- Sketchbook, undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
- Sketchbook, undated (Box 22, Folder 2)
- Sketchbook, undated (Box 22, Folder 3)
- Exhibitions and Publications, 2002-2022; cuid39028 (Box 24, Folder 1-9, Box Electronic Records, Item FA_MSS_338_ER_1)